[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
um all right everyone welcome to the
stoa i'm peter lindberg the steward of
the stoa and the store is a place for us
to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this very moment
and today we're very lucky because we
have peter jones
visiting the stoa peter jones is an
associate professor
of systemic design at ocad university
which is in toronto where he teaches the
strategic foresight and innovation
and design for health programs um
and he leads innovative research and
flourishing economies
uh cultural sustainability healthcare
system design complex social system
design throughout ocad
and through his innovative research firm
the redesign
network uh and the title of today's talk
is living through the global problematic
um which i'm sure peter will introduce
in a moment and he'll discuss evolution
of the
global problematic which is a framework
for complex
societal problems um so how today is
going to work
peter's going to present for about 35
minutes
and then any time when peter's talking
you can throw your questions
in the chat i will call on you and mute
yourself
ask your question to peter if you want
to read it on your behalf because this
will go on youtube
uh just let me know and i'll read it on
your behalf that being said
i will allow peter to unmute himself
and take him in welcome to the store
excellent thank you peter um
and uh we are blessed and cursed
to live in truly unusual times
i'm delighted to join the stoa for
for a talk i've participated in several
other talks on the other
side and i i love how the community is
going
and so as being somebody who's kind of
local in this virtual space as well
um living in toronto in greek town and
teaching at ocad downtown when we did
have a downtown to teach in
um i i thought that i would uh bring
at least for a first talk to the stoa um
uh some of the ideas that um underpin
the the development of of my view of
systemic design
of the discipline that i've been
developing and teaching
at ocad the strategic foresight
innovation program
and that goes back to my my uh
years as a phd student and working with
uh
dr um alecko alexander christakis
who is around at the formation of the
club of rome and so
kind of i wasn't a young pup but as a
middle-aged pup or whatever working with
aleco i heard a lot of
the stories of the club of rome how it
was formed how it didn't really achieve
uh all the goals that that his school of
systems thinkers thought that it might
have
and and i've uh i've done my own
interrogation in this
you know into that history and and and
it makes an interesting story because of
the situations that we're facing today
and this is also the 50th anniversary
year
of the club of rome's um
momentous meeting which is actually in
new york
uh they defined their major agenda for
um for the their uh
major study based on a prospectus
developed
by hassan ozbakan uh known as the the
predicament of mankind
and and the predicament of mankind was
uh the brief if you will the design
brief
presented to the club of rome as the the
framework from which
um uh several different proposals might
be
might be presented and hasano's pecan's
proposal was built into the brief itself
so he's probably as he was chosen to um
present the the formulation of this
prospectus
um he you know he also used as the
opportunity to
to kind of sell his own approach and i
think that
you know that um he wasn't selected
uh for the club of rome's study
as we know the limits to growth was but
but in that prospectus he developed an
approach to
social systems design which is which is
really
has been with us since and has actually
helped spawn
a different school of systems thinking
that has existed in parallel since that
time
and and it has quite a bit of quite a
bit of life
left into it uh today i think so i want
to uh
i want to say a little bit about the
term the problematic um
you may have heard that in other
references before and it
it is associated with both a systems
model and a method of representation
so the probability is kind of a thing
that represents
uh the relationships of complex societal
systems
to each other a mapping of them and then
it's also
in a generic term how we represent that
type of complex
mapping and it was a and hassan osbikon
was a fairly understated and it was well
known his own community but kind of a
think tanker
of the 1960s he was the um
he was the inventor of a field that back
then was called normative planning
that led into social systems design and
and his his mapping out of the
problematic was a way to
create a frame for sense making that is
still i think very robust
today a framework that
at that time and i think still absorbs
all the crises and conditions
of modernity's transition from
from 1970 was a really clearly a
transition period for a lot of the
critical conditions that were mapped out
in in
the global problematic as as it was
called
and today we can see ourselves
collectively entangled in
in in the similar world system if you
look at
how the problematique was formed if you
actually look up his paper
which you can do as a google search on
the predicament of mankind
without even spelling osmakon you'll
find just a few references to it which
are probably my friends that
hold copies of this paper and so any
meaning
of you know of of this phrase this and
this kind of entanglement of the problem
fatigue presents us with a view of the
mega crisis a cluster
of interrelated crisis effects and these
are not
core issues that is they're not driving
root cause issues
they are very far from it they are they
are the results of many years
of of of effects being
effects interconnecting to other effects
and let's say
and and we can conceive of this with
other you know with new terms
uh today we through geoscience consider
this
kind of period of the mega crisis as as
entering the anthropocene
uh and and i see actually the mega
crisis is
as as a way of viewing uh the
problematic is a
much larger set of wicked problems or
a coffee and messes or riddles wicked
problems or the
idea of the the super wicked problem of
climate change as
it's as it has been recently referenced
uh
but i would say that the global
problematic is perhaps
understated in its representation of
these
kind of terrifying crises conditions
that we consider today because in 1970
even then it included climate and
environment as
separate single problem clusters they
were
uh among the 49 continuous critical
problems
and each one and they were in and of
themselves
you know issues that were interconnected
with those other issues
and so depending on how we view
criticality that is
of what issues are critical to address
and how and how we design to them there
are
several different modes to define
several ways
to define criticality as temporal
leverage
that is a urgency of now or the urgency
of taking action
in the near term in order to make
progressive action over longer term
impacts
um ozbekon was was very concerned with
that that in 1970 believed we needed to
take action
now on some of these not all of them
didn't believe you could address all
49 of the of the plot problem clusters
kind of as a whole
but to think about them as a whole of
connections
and to find critical leverages and
actually this is before they applied the
system dynamics models
of uh foresters mit group and the limits
to growth so they didn't even call it
leverage
then that wasn't a term used so much
where i think even in the problematic
um or in the predicament document they
talked about feedback imbalances pretty
much the same thing
and that and so the goal of the the pro
the global problem boutique was to
identify places where there would be
significant critical imbalances in
economy
and food production in in war and
conflict
in in governance and policy in
population
and you know in uh in in
many aspects of resource use and food
production and all these drivers
would impinge on other outcomes
that could be even less
survivable so that the outcomes could
the effects
of these problem systems if you will
would be would themselves be very
uh would become uh critical issues and
so there was a
an intent in the early stages of this
you know trying to identify the issues
in the problem fatigue
of what is critical what to address uh
early in first so that we could make
progress across the entire mapping of of
of those issues to each other and i
usually present this with you know
plenty of pictures and i show them you
know show the
uh oz becons um kind of you know um
crude view graph pictures from the 1970s
and some updates of mappings of the 49
continuous critical problems
and because kind of the tradition in the
is to just
spell it out in words i want to give you
more of a
of the impression of of uh
of how you know well some details about
the problematic but more of impression
of why it's critical
rather than attending to the specific um
continuous critical problems themselves
but but i also want to tie this to some
other issues that i think are continuing
within
um that we hear a lot within others
talks in the stoa so i mean we um
we're interested in in criticality and
in
resolution but not problem solving which
is
going to be a distinction i'll bring up
again this is not a matter of problem
solving that problematic even though
it's
named that way so what we're trying to
do is to
over all these years and this is now the
50th anniversary of this kind of
mode we're interested in um
in dealing with and and offsetting the
possible collapse scenarios that
attend this mega crisis the collapse
scenarios in
ecology and economy politics and society
culture of course civilization
the dynamics of collapse have been
developed
well by other scholars uh system
scientist joseph
tainter and and timothy allen the
ecologists and botanists by economists
george skew erosion in the in the 1980s
and and and recently the um economics uh
blogger
uh charles hughes smith who i really
recommend
are you know who's writing about this
quite often
um and if you don't find smith i mean he
he boils this down into bite-sized
pieces and with graphs
and so really brings it to life and and
also
authors you may have heard of you know
of course thomas homer dixon
the upside of down jared diamond's
collapse dimitri orlov's
kind of cycles of of collapse and these
are all scholars that
have really worked with the ideas that
came out of the global problematic but
have addressed them in terms of their
effects
um at this point but and so there were a
number of
social theories and historical cyclic
theories
um strauss house fourth turning david
corton's great turning
peter turchin's structural demographics
cycles and models these are all useful
informants and models some of which
might even
help us act so i mean that's
as a design professor and training
designer designers at the masters level
this is really where we're trying to
connect this so the history i think is
is important to to address but and is
kind of
interesting to bring forward but you
know what can we
what should we really do to act and it's
an ethical issue
um so the best of these collapse
scenarios really reveal
transdisciplinary
dynamics uh relationships that enable us
to
perceive the multiple dimensions of the
problem fatigue as a whole
so we can work it so we have to
work with different stakeholders
sometimes called experts as well that
may be
experts in different disciplines but
then working across those disciplines to
have an understanding
across multiple perspectives in order to
make sense of this type of a
complex set of dynamics and so this
essential frame of the global
problematic you can think of is
overlapping manifold complicated
pro and complex problems for which we
register consensus
and the political concern based on on
some consensus that we have
um that we have agreement on what what
these you know what today's problems
might be
and so we can see variations of
strategic foresight at work
in that is in the orientations
um to the global problematic in the last
decade of social problem agendas we've
seen the united nations development
program
um um the agenda 2030 in the development
of
of of the sustainable development goals
following the millennial
millennium development goals and the md
mdgs were considered i guess kind of an
on-ramp they probably weren't really a
successful program but
as these things go they got rolled
forward into a
significant emphasis in the sdg program
which
let's see from the badge here i'm
somewhat um
involved with with a number of different
groups that i'm engaged in
it has become um perhaps
the the you know the most well-known
framework for the representation of
of um of dealing with
the global problematic today we hardly
ever hear the term the problematic but
we
you will hear and you are hearing about
the sustainable development goals is
perhaps the most
notable and successful problem system
or framing of a problem system today but
we're in 2020
um this is the year that was the year of
the future
when we started the strategic foresight
innovation program in 2009
uh 2008 our first students in 2009 and
all of our first
work in the strategic innovation lab in
scenarios for
future uh future scenario constructs and
for contract work and
and shirk projects and and such for for
for a lot of our lab work 2020 was
always
out of the the clever decade ahead and
then it was five years ahead and it's
like we
didn't actually budge the pointer to the
future
as we got closer to it i have seen
just speaking from my own experience as
someone who works in strategic foresight
as
um or adapts strategic foresight methods
into
everything from municipal planning and
community energy planning complex
sustainability
strategic planning you know
we push for longer term time frames and
almost in
all cases if we're working with
a third horizon models that is first
second and third horizon different time
frames
of of um time horizons
that are overlapping into um
longer horizon futures in which these
problems would be resolved
the if we take a third horizon of 50
years
into a planning context can guarantee
that we'll be asked to
break it down into a 10-year plan at
best at longest
and so so this is where i i feel that
now we're in 2020 and we're facing
kind of the results of of several
different
crises that have that have been pinched
just within this year
and in different failures that we can
see that
it's safe to say that um
that many of the scenarios we were
planning for for 2020 didn't actually
happen
as we as we proposed in the different
in the way that we can envision
uncertainties
over a 10-year period we aren't aiming
for prediction
but for scenarios which will give us
insight
and give our clients insight for being
able to
address options as they may occur
as those scenarios may appear scenarios
may appear and then with respect to the
the
the work of the club of rome on the
global problematique
they didn't actually conduct this type
of um
scenario planning instead they ran
system dynamics models
on on um you know on
on variables that were simulated to to
present
various simulation outcomes for the
relationship of the
of a subset of those issues in the 49
continuous critical problems
so i'd ask do we face the decade of
now coming up to 2030 with hope and
engagement
or with trepidation and dread or some
odd mix of both which is
probably more the case and
we might in our communities of inquiry
consider
developing a view of the planetary mega
crisis
in a way that that that as
that is another type of meta crisis with
its
that we have spoken about in the stella
a meta crisis being a view
above and over and containing some
understanding and having
a distance view from the collapses of
meaning
of telos of direction of
ontology of of of relationship
in civitas of the systemic fragility
these i would say are are outcomes of
these issues that were identified you
know many years ago but they're
um but they're not the causes and so in
that
the causes themselves are so far distant
from
from the situation we're in today so let
me go back to
kind of how the mega crisis was formed
and named
uh as a global problematic by
hassan ozmakan it was kind of a
brilliant understated scholar that not a
lot of people
even know of he had he didn't have that
many publications and most of the
writings that really made a huge
difference i think
um uh that i that you can find of his
are from the 1960s and before the club
of rome so as the scholar of a general
theory
of normative planning that is that he
developed
in in the late 1960s a view of
of long horizon futures
oriented planning that would take into
account um
strategy operations and the normative
view
and so in this in the late 60s hassan
had drafted
the concepts the early concepts of a
global problematic with 27
um critical continuous problems
and and those and within two years were
expanded of course just to be
whether or not to be dramatic but he
added um
he added uh over 20 more to construct a
final
set which is presented the club of rome
in 1969 1970
as the 49 and just to read a few of
these
in their terms i mean they included um
pop uh population growth uh urban sprawl
widespread poverty insufficient
education
the increasing lethality of weapons um
uh the general i and this is some of his
wording anachronistic and
irrelevant education generalized
alienation of youth
um ideological fragmentation semantic
barriers to communication between
individuals groups and nations
inadequate participation of people at
large in public decisions
and a lot of these sound like if they
could be addressed
would have significant impact on the
resolution of the other
kind of major effects in that in that
set
but he also included um
a a small number of very provocative
issues
well the ideological fragmentation i
think is notable but um
obsolete institutional arrangements of
course the failure of imagination
and the failure to understand the nature
of continuous critical problems
so we proposed this set as an
illustrated illustrative list
that is it was just meant to be a list
of
of problem clusters but not problems in
and of themselves and as
clusters each one of them was conceived
of containing
its own problematique so
obsolete institutional arrangements
would be like a tree with many branches
and roots that would have its own issues
but that would be entangled with
all of the others and that he saw them
interacting globally
regionally interdependently and inter
sensitive that is that they they
touched each other in ways that could
not be
easily perceived by experts or others
that but that would have
you know like butterfly wing complexity
effects on the others
and that they were immune to linear
problem solving
or cause that and causal analysis
that is that any attempt to redress
these issues through a linear problem
solving was bound to fail
and i think that still is the case and
the inside of the global problem
in nineteen was that in 1970 the this
kind of temporal urgency
was considered that the window of time
in which any
of those um major issues could be
recognized and ameliorated at the time
um as discreet societal concerns
was passing that there is a window of
time in which you could actually address
obsolete institutional arrangements or
insufficient
um education for the time or
uh i guess they were addressing poverty
with a great society around that time
and that been programs like that but
these were more he was looking at more
the root cause some of the or the
the deeper issues that where we could
really take action
and he was saying that if as that window
passed that all of these
issues were going to become entangled
and
evolved from these discrete matters of
concern
into overlapping interconnected problem
clusters
that became eventually as we might even
see today
a non-decomposable whole problem system
of problems
uh generating itself gender continuing
to
so we often think of autopilots this is
like a cool form of self-organization
and also problems self-organize and they
self-reproduce and they
and they interact with each other in the
same way that living systems do
these types of of systems can be seen to
do that
and so we're dealing with an almost
entirely outcome effects
of multi effects so you know so
to test this notion uh consider for
yourselves you know
how we are attempting to address climate
change now
i mean except in some of the i'm also
a board member of the project drawdown
in toronto
drawdown toronto has been trying to
educate people in the
scientific solutions scientifically
based range of solutions for addressing
um carbon impacts through creative and
scientific approaches that can actually
be done locally
but most of the way the climate crisis
has been
kind of framed is that we're dealing
with large policy issues and
carbon credits and trading and carbon
policy
at national levels but we're dealing
with an effect
system here that is the ultimate outcome
of
decades of decades of
problem systems upon problem of
multi-causal inputs
and drivers leading to how you know this
ultimate system of effects and yet
you know what we're what sometimes it
seems to me that the movements are
attempting to do are to push for
what might be a single solution silver
bullet such as
carbon dioxide reduction okay
you know i mean we want to see that as a
measure but that is not a solution
in and of itself and and this is where i
think some of
the thinking that comes from taking into
account
you know the entire problem you know and
the entire problematic is a way of
of better resolving that so when these
kinds of
when these large large-scale problem
systems overwhelm our cognitive and
problem-solving capacities
we over simplify we look for some silver
bullets
uh or as my my mentor uh christakis's
colleague john warfield like to say we
under conceptualize and when we work
together in um in in groups
we under conceptualize even more so we
you know so it makes it hard to even uh
collaborate
and develop collective you know collect
approaches to collective
wisdom for amelioration because we are
you know we we become um
you know our our conceptualization our
modes of of problem solving become even
more restricted
in some ways so we need creative ways of
of actually engaging
i'll say more about that in a bit let me
say something about i want to tell you a
quick story
about the club of rome a few minutes
here
about how that formed and how that has
kind of led us to today
so the history of the club of rome lends
insight into how we form
global action networks today so i might
have mentioned there are a number of
groups that are global action networks
and
multi stakeholder multi-expert groups
that are addressing
uh the sustainable development goals in
different ways i probably belong to five
of these different groups um maybe two
in canada
three internationally and so these uh
the club of rome is probably the
earliest
group formed in 1970 that dealt with the
that created you know international
global problem solving frame and it had
in its
roots the uh the oecd
approaches to policy management at the
time and leading policy institutions of
the 60s
it was quite technocratic and i think
that also result resulted in the
approaches that we're seeing in kind of
big system projects
you know very much in the 1960s frame of
the best and the brightest
the club of rome was formed by the
executive committee alexander king who
was the oecd
science advisor from throughout the
1960s
um very well respected system scientist
and
and um and um uh
and uh aurelio piche was that
uh pache was the uh ex the chief
executive of fiat at the time as well as
hugo thiemann from battelle in
switzerland
they convened a series of workshops in
bellagio with eric yanch who was
also at with oecd at the time and as
they grew that
um apparently those workshops
were kind of fumbling through but they
led to a point where
they formed they wanted to form convene
kind of this
meeting of leading systems thinkers to
address
you know the predicament of mankind as
as it was called and so the first
they drew together uh hassan ozbekon was
well known from the system
system development corporation think
tank jay forrester from mit
dennis gabor renee dubow an environment
early environmentalist systems thinker
and the first club of rome
framed those concepts the first concepts
of the planetary emergency
and the original prospectus of the club
of rome then was written by hassan
osbahn as an open brief as
the um as and it was essentially
competed with
mit for this roughly one million dollar
uh prize to produce the first study for
the club of rome
and so the global problem you could be
seen as the first
formal agreement about the high priority
global issues
of the time um the first agreement as to
what those would be
and and ospicon had published those
ideas earlier but then he was invited by
the executive committee to prepare that
brief to pitch it and
frame it and his approach was
and this might give you an idea why it
wasn't selected why limits to growth was
is that is that um had very high minded
ideals the
aim to achieve ecological balance and to
define what that might mean on a global
scale
through understanding the deep system
relations and designing new policies
that would
help address ecological balance on a
world system scale
to engage the requisite variety of
multiple stakeholders
beyond experts but to uh hassan osbicom
believed that
it was unethical to design social
systems without the direct
contribution of the stakeholders it
would affect and how do you do this in a
world
system scale you believe that you needed
to define
the values base that people would agree
would be the values that would be
constructed that we would work through
for the new for the systems
change that would guide ethical decision
making
um it was a serious analytical project
at the same time to discover
felicitous relationships between um
the the 49 continuous critical problems
their synergies
their underlying you know root issues
and what we would call leverage analysis
today
uh to develop he had a strong critique
of the problem-solving mindset
he said you can't you we will never
resolve these issues
through problem solving and we got in
fact the word problem is problematic
and it's the problematic is problematic
but
he kept trying to push back on the
technocratic tendency to decompose and
solve everything difficult in 1970
because that's
that as you know has persist through 50
years
and he called for new modes of reasoning
and planning relational
modes of reasoning and stakeholder
groups feedback
feed forward futures creative modes of
of engagement you know proposing
idealized futures
all modes of reasoning but especially
abductive reasoning which is really
design mode
and we know from the well documented
history of the limits to growth
project that um the executive committee
chose
jay forrester's proposal the mit
proposal and the mit team has also
been famously composed of dennis and
danella meadows
jurgen randers all had different skills
that they brought in the team but
within two years the limits to growth
study was
was actually produced and it was formed
on the basis of running
state-of-the-art simulations of pri of a
small set of
primary variables that they believe were
underlying the pro
problematic so the public success of the
limits to growth was evident in the
rapid progress that was
made to publish uh within two years this
publicly accessible non-technical
exposition
of actually system dynamics models that
were run
based on the world model simulation and
what was
really powerful about that simulation as
presented or was it created a mental
model that
that readers of the limits to growth
could then
act on or or would would take into
account when you spoke of the limits to
growth people knew what that meant
um and it had in a in a created
an idea of the future prospect of these
these um critical tipping points and
collapse points which
which were stated under different
assumptions in different scenario
conditions which we're seeing happen
now essentially in 2020 which was kind
of the critical
crossing over point in in the in the
standard
and typical model so this basic behavior
mode was
of the limits to growth was an
exponential
which was a model exponential growth of
population in capital
followed by a collapse and in these
scenarios this typical run
shows multiple collapses occurring right
about like 2020. you can just see
the crossover points the sudden
industrial output
population of food peak
pollution peak which was in a high peak
but it started to decline because
production was declining
and declines in resources and capital as
well
as population had peaked and then
so their their assumptions in the early
70s they did well enough with the
information available
and it made a compelling story the
dynamics of it still seemed to be proven
even to some extent even if their um
assumptions
and actual data were not but they were
hugely criticized for their malthusian
assumptions about the global limitations
of production
that as it did not foresee the huge
synergies that were going to
actually develop in technological
development
the proposed overshoot and collapse
model as well that was also later
developed by people like um
um ecological economists captain
nicholas uh george georges q rojan
that was redelent of marx's predictions
of the failure of capitalism it just fed
right into
you know marxist scholarship and that
this is this is predicting the failure
of capitalism right
but unfortunately for the predicament of
humanity such a
positivist and hard scientist hard
science presentation
created a huge target for growth
capitalism
and mainstream um liberalism
as well so it was technologists managers
especially economists
just you know pushed back hard the below
political blowback was such that the
limits to growth
went into submergence or submerged
really for
another 20 years or more and it didn't
really really return in kind of serious
discourse to any extent until the
30-year review in 2002.
i mean environmentalists and ecological
economists were still discussing it and
had some growth in the 90s but not
really on a big
you know it started to come back as
actually its predictions started to come
back
now here i want to say hassano's bacon's
proposal remember i said
his proposal to the club of rome was
rejected it was hugely ambitious
it was insanely insightful i encourage
you to read the whole thing
and but it was considered unduly complex
uh
overreaching um under under
developed methodologically you know we
had insights into methodology there was
no method yet
for or no technology for suitable
engagement of stakeholders
um and it and it was under
conceptualized in terms of how it
actually might be
you know perform conducted as a million
dollar study
so so what happened with kind of the
rejection
of you know of the author of the
the prospectus itself this leads to the
dynamics of the motivated also ran
and i've been one of those and maybe you
have to which is you put a lot of
investment into a pretty significant
project
and at some point it gets rejected and
at that point you've like
invested and learned you know half a
year or year's worth of
engagement and what do you do with that
so
so this proposal his proposal and his
approaches leading up to this is so
far-reaching and promising that
there were a small school of system
scientists that
that including eric yanch who kind of
left the club of rome to to work on
other things
um um and my mentor uh
aleco christakis and his colleague john
warfield
who were part of that circle you know
that
in the nascent field of social systems
design
and so where the typical view of systems
thinking schools consists of
you know hard systems which are system
based on system dynamics and system
modeling
soft systems or you know checklines soft
systems methodology
critical systems um critical systems
theory i guess you could say post modern
but as well as cybernetics and
complexity
yeah i'm just gonna flake uh we reached
the 40-minute mark
oh okay oh let me uh let me wrap with uh
some
some wrapping up points because the sure
the key to this is
all of this is this is a school of
systems theory that people don't really
know too much about
but this has been developed kind of in
us in a slow way over many years and
then as
and has had it's so it's still got a
life of its own
um and so hassan went on to consulting
at wharton
and and he ended up dying he died in
um i think the same year is actually his
kind of his rival
rasakov also passed away but what hassan
was missing
was an engagement process which is
essentially what i've been trying to
develop ever since and with
with um um uh with eleko christakis's
work
which came out of this work from the
1970s
stock has developed software for
engaging a debt for democratic
engagement as stakeholders which was
essentially it has been developed from
like
dos packages in the in the 90s to
windows packages to now
online and web system so just to wrap up
let me say i think
a long view like this helps us keep a
cool head
under the uncertainties and
extraordinaries of the current era
and uh my own networks have taken me
into multiple projects where
this viewpoint has certainly helped um i
think there are
you know if we look at the sdgs today
the sustainable development goals as a
kind of simplistic solution oriented
approach it helps to
also can consider the complex problem
fatigue behind that that is the
the the ways of problem resolution that
we could identify
leverages and relationships that could
make significant progress towards some
of them
and to reach all of them and so the sdgs
i think is
a laudable but broad sweep approach
there are a number of system mapping
projects going on right now trying to
identify these leverages including one
with a former graduate student of mine
that i'm trying that i'm working with
but the key issue a few key issues we
need to know is how do we stop solving
the wrong problems
are we focused on the right problems are
we um
if these problems are so interconnected
how do we address the right
level of leverage where do we go
in how do we design processes for
addressing that can we proceed from a
normative frame like ospecon had
suggested
or demanded what ought we to do
how do we discover our values base how
do we
critique the problem solving mindset um
how do we
how do we address the assumptions of
problem uh
were like le tour perhaps identifying
them rethinking them as matters of
concern and not
problems and so i would kind of leave it
i can leave it there i guess to open it
up for
for questions and discussion as to
really what ought we do because i guess
my answers are design of course systemic
design at that but
so let me just take a few questions from
there and and have some discussion with
you
great uh yeah we have a lot of delicious
questions for
a delicious topic are you just if we
have 15 minutes of the hour are you okay
to
like hang out like 10 15 minutes after
the hour or yeah i am if people are
yeah okay cool so we'll feel it out um
dan you had a question just got a plus
one if you can unmute yourself
um wait
i seem to have a few uh yeah
um
thank you very much peter i asked a
bunch of questions
i'm hearing an echo of myself here i'm
sorry um
i'll go and mute for a sec what's my
question i asked like three or four
questions
um
is the model that oz khan presented
is it's was the approach
and the framing too cognitively
cognitively
complex for most people to
really understand what he was trying to
do
uh and then it lacked that simplicity
that's one question
and then the other question is which i
didn't ask which was
is at the base of the design you know
the approach of how to go about this
one of the things that i'm discovering
in similar areas is this
all comes down to values at the very
beginning
and some people have a a model
that humans are just greedy selfish
beings and therefore incessant infinite
growth
is just a given and they have to just
kind of trust in the market
to save us all and the idea
that you know we should organize around
prince values of dignity and well-being
for each and
all and integrity um
is kind of like disney world thinking
and i'm wondering
if that if these issues are issues that
you've encountered or if you have any
perspective on how to address those oh
yeah thanks dan
yeah first of all um hassan osakan was
probably
was actually 50 years ahead of his time
um
a colleague had started to
compose a biography of his work which
was hard to do
we have access to his archives but he
didn't publish very many papers maybe
five and some of them are like what we
would call blogs today
but if you read his um the general
theory of
of planning from 1969
1967 the triumph of technology
and the prospectus of the
club the predicament of of mankind
itself
this is less than 40 pages they are
dense and brilliantly conceived and they
are
you know just so i think concisely
framed that it's not just
it's not that it was complex it was just
in a language that people weren't ready
to
grasp very well um the first generation
systems thinkers did not suffer fools
i've
i didn't go to wharton but i've talked
to people i i
make it a point to talk with people who
have studied who
were um lucky enough to study with osama
khan in the 70s and 80s
and he was difficult he was
extremely difficult and you'd think a
lot of this
would be almost qualitative and it was
qualitative and
quantitative and so he was very rigorous
and demanding and so i think some of
that was also
you know so was probably forrester but
maybe mit had more of a team approach
and ospicon wasn't really known for
collaboration
so much but he was he was a formidable
thinker
and and people and everyone who knew
them said that this was
well ahead of their time and so the
approach to the
limits to growth took probably was a way
of actually
saving what could have been a very
complex
project if hassan had actually led it i
mean maybe
you know eric yanch and warfield and
christophers would have come together
for it i don't know what team he would
have made
and maybe they would have formed created
the software then
but what actually happened is they
developed that software with patel
later but without hassan but they stayed
these these guys tended to stay in touch
with each other
but i found and also with warfield
christakis it was
those you could never put two of these
guys in the room together
they're just very huge people so there
is that they
they expected you to be able to follow
but
so so they conceived very conceived big
um and also the complexity of what might
be done the technology wasn't there at
the time
and so the limits to growth was a way of
you know eight
variables run on computer simulation
you know you know using system dynamics
modeling at the time which is still what
you might do today um
and then uh hassan's um key insight
about working from the value spaces i
mean that's actually one of the things
that inspired
my own phd research in embedded values
and organizations and i agree with you
that that is
that is it is not just the place to
start it is a place to start but you
have to continue to un
to um return to values it's not like
i it's not like a research project to
survey
you know instrumental and and um
you know instrumental and ontological
and
and formal values within
organizations and individuals and kind
of map them and identify priorities
i mean you can do that
but this um stakeholder but a true
stakeholder engagement approach has to
respect the requisite variety of people
stakeholders that are invested in the
uh decisions and the outcomes of the
problem system that they're
that they're working with and so you
know in the in the the software process
of dialogic design
we tend to do that and there's some work
on the values in advance
of getting people together into a room
or into
a virtual engagement and so that
we understand what types of values
conflicts might take
you know take shape in that and i think
there's to also add one
more thing to that i didn't mention i
sort of dropped bruno latour
in talking about matters of concern
which is from his
a cautious prometheus paper about design
from 2008
but in what was it 2014 2015 we wrote
um an inquiry into modes of existence
which is
about the different ontology uh
ontological
um values sets the
essentially 14 15 different modes of
existence
and that how we have to understand those
in order to compose a common world and
to re-establish
trust in institutions needless to say
that didn't happen but
i think that those are some models that
are very consistent with
what those pecan wanted to do and i
think that is a place to start
and end
all right um on john you had a
question
[Music]
um hey peter we we had dave snowden on
the
stowa over the last month and he's uh
he's kind of a curmudgeon
and he made an interesting comment um
he basically contrasted systems thinking
with complexity
and said system thinking he's like ah a
bunch of schmucks
because what they try to do is model
future scenarios and work backwards
you thought complexity makes more sense
because what it tries to do is map the
the present and work towards an
attractor in following energy gradients
i'm curious what you think of snowden's
framing and how you see
complexity and systems thinking fit
together in contrast
i understand that model i think it also
fits with kanavan
model as well and i teach that and bring
that into the classroom so my
you know my students will understand
that as well
how i view the approach is not
systems as systems thinking but as well
um the relationship of of systems theory
as an underpinning to design
and so design is is a way of of
working with complexity that is
probably certainly consistent with
complexity theory and with with dave
snowden's model
and i think he probably views it as a
type of design
but him he's more of a a planner
and a complexity scientist in in his
in his work and and and i do work with
design
you know with large-scale design
projects with information design
system and service design and so i
i look you know what we've formed in the
last decade is
is a relationship of of compatible
systems theories that actually do take
into account
um strategic foresight and back casting
feedback and feed forward leverage
analysis
and complexity in cybernetics principles
where they apply so like
good designers we look at the principles
um i have a paper from 2014 on
on systemic design principles for
complex social systems
and i've identified 10 overlapping
principles that are shared between
systems complexity and cybernetics but i
call them systems principles
and that that are shared with design
principles
so those are like um ideal an
idealized system um boundary framing
so a brief is a as a framing but
boundary critique is a systems method um
like um requisite variety ought to be a
design principle so i just leave it in
ashby's
mode because it's still a frame still
chord cybernetics and complexity
as well um appreciating complexity
uh you know
generative feedback uh compositional
design
these are ways of approaching
kind of both both fields so that they
can
they can so i think of it simply put as
as a compatible systems theory that
supports effective
design for complex contexts and we've
had a conference for the last nine years
on this
rsd relating systems thinking and design
which is actually next week so i can put
my plug in there now that if you look up
rsd9.org um
it will show a conference being
sponsored in national institute of
design in
india who's one of our one of our
partners from the very beginning
helping kind of frame the theory
practice and research base
that is that is developed and if you
look at our past
um projects so i'd say even dave
dave snowed on a look at the proceedings
of the last
eight years and some of our keynotes
that include
like ranolf glanville and uh and uh
john john thakura and and uh the
um and my mentor christakis as well as
umberto
machurana remotely and we had uh when i
sponsored the conference in toronto
uh paul panguero eric stolderman
you know so that a range of designers
and systems thinkers and
in design and as well as i think
i share this maybe interest
with the stoa um you know we're also
getting as much as possible
um legacy thinkers while we can
you know so randolph-glenville gave his
last talk
yet he had cancer he died three weeks
after his talk in oslo
in 2014 and um
and alecko probably isn't traveling very
much anymore and you know
and there are a number i'd like to get
we have vandashiva by the time she was
speaking
um you know virtually but in this
conference
so it's cheap it's in india so i'd
encourage you but that's where i'm
that's where i think
that's where my future interests are and
that's what i think resolves
the conflicts between those
those disciplines because i'm trying to
work in a different interdiscipline
all right um uh andre you want to do a
quick follow-up
um feel free to punt if we don't have
enough time i was just gonna ask peter
just
from kind of your personal experience
how do you like
have so many models and not get
overwhelmed um
i'm always what is the personal mo in
habits
i'm older at some of it is is you
develop them over time
i mean um if i tried to embrace all
those when i first started
um and they become additive and and then
get
constructed uh through dialogue and
conversation
and i and and and some people go depth
first
and i'm more breadth-first and then i
continue to cycle
over them as i get develop more interest
and i look for projects where i can
apply them
so i'll keep you know so for many years
i had like a
a pervasive but not deep interest
in anarchy and ecological systems but
then it became
essential so i was kind of hovering and
circling around
you know hollis and gunderman
ecological economics but then i started
working on a project with uh
an ecological economist for what we now
call the flourishing business model the
strong
designing business models for strong
sustainability in the integration of
social
social economic and environmental
impacts that are all considered between
stakeholders the value proposition in
the business
that required developing you know
knowledge deeper knowledge in those
system
in that system model so you go deeper
when you need to
in the meantime you get conversant with
other people so you can hold a
conversation i guess and
but also i've been you know living with
some of these models since
um it's high school and they started
reading like arty lange
and gregory bateson just out of interest
because some of my
smart smart aleck friends were
you know reading that in high school and
we'd pass
like politics of experience would get
passed around like some secret doctrine
it was mind-blowing i didn't realize
that was systems theory and you find out
later
as these ideas start to continue to blow
your mind that they make sense and
they build on each other and so you get
converse
we have also a community of practice
which is
now virtual held the second monday of
every
month um systems thinkers ontario and we
have
um speakers like david hawk and me and
david ing
david ing and i have been co-evolving
that's his
handle co-evolving that since uh i guess
seven years now
and there's also um i think it's the
second tuesday so after that monday the
next
very next second tuesday is the strongly
sustainable business model group which
is about 2 000 people
internationally and we have regular like
leading speakers there
so if you're interested in those you
could either reach out to me or just
look
kind of google them and see what comes
up because each of those sites has wikis
st on dot wiki and ssbmg wiki
we'll tell you about the next upcoming
sessions so those
communities of practice help us you know
um continue to just hold ongoing
discussions about uh and and like
journal clubs will read papers
discuss them um sharpen just like in the
stoa
and sharpen our our interest or
attention but i wrote the
the systemic design principles paper
i was actually very nervous about
putting that into the field because i
hadn't
published strongly in the systems you
know in
kind of the systems domain yet i mean
actually i had before but
it was radically different and i wasn't
sure it was going to be accepted and so
this the the systems thinking ontario
group
like spent two sessions reading it and
critiquing it and talking about it and
made it super strong and
i don't know if the stoic could do that
with somebody's paper but
we do things like that and i think that
you know i would i would recommend
you know in the store using these ideas
just to sharpen
our insights in that same way and and
the models that we have so they
they grow over time and create
conceptual frameworks that
they fit into and they become more
natural
but we always continue i'm always
continue to be just blown away by those
who are depth first
so many people that that have gone so
deep into a few models that just you
know
that it's just not my style and i'll
have a few that are deep but
you know it takes there's there are
different skills
so just tell you who i admire there
awesome thanks
um so we'll have time for maybe one more
question uh
tim you had a question and i'll copy and
paste in the chats below
yeah hi peter um thanks for the weaving
together of
history and all these different topics
it's been really interesting um
you may know that uh i'm a designer and
i spend a lot of time
thinking about um this problem boutique
as you framed it
um and i so i was really interested to
see this um
topic around uzbekon and um
i'm really concerned that uh the
language that
and the framings the problem framings
that we're all using are effectively
um causing the system to
that we live in to self-perpetuate and
so i'm curious
how you might suggest that we all
approach these kinds of issues and you
kind of alluded to the fact that like
for the un
and the sdgs for example are kind of a
simplistic framing
and i see them as speaking of um baits
in them
as logical type errors in that they're
framed around consequences
and not conditions right so it they
don't really
acknowledge even in their framing
um the interconnectedness and the cross
contextuality of the
of the of the problem of the problem
fatigue itself and so
how how do we get away from this
uh sort of tendency that you you
spent your essentially the entire talk
talking about um
this oversimplification in this like um
winnowing things down into these uh we
start looking for these silver bullet
solutions and so that's the question
like how to
how to essentially even in the framing
get away from this
uh perpetuating the system that we live
in
it's a very big question that would be a
good way to actually introduce an
entirely different talk which is uh
which is essentially
knowing this what are we to do and that
would also involve
aesthetics and ethics and dialogue
and virtues ontologies
now and framing and so i've suggested
some approaches that i like and some
ways of i think addressing
ways to um
ways to um uh
work around the problem-solving mindset
the consequentialist approach to
for example the to um account for that
accounts for
the the um uh oh
the simplistic kind of policy oriented
framing
of the 17 uh sustainable development
goals
there are many kind of problematic
um aspects to the sdgs that i didn't
even start to address but probably the
biggest
the the biggest problem of framing is
that they're called
sustainable development goals which
really
you know uh shows their relationship
going back to the 1986 brotland report
of of um our you know our
our common are common earth and which
was good at the time
and framing sustainable development as
the approach that
world institutions ought to be using to
address
um at that time the problematic and that
may not have been considered a
problem-solving approach but what
happened was sustainable development
became conceived as more
what we would see in in an industrial
organizational approach to managing
policy outcomes
to address you know the the effects
of these problem systems which which is
and you're right it is a it is a a
a category error and that makes it very
hard to
um it makes it very hard to reframe
because everybody
you can assume in almost any engagement
around the sdgs has already bought into
the sdgs
the one way that i've been addressing uh
kind of a a feed forward approach to the
sustainable development goals and the
program itself
is to engage in working with some of the
some of the
kind of the new economies programs that
are
willing to go into and address
sdg eight which actually is about
economic growth relative to different
um geographic contexts and i think that
that's a problematic sdg because it is
framed around economic growth and it
doesn't
allow for the new new frames of
economic systems to emerge and so
i've it it also just so happens that a
graduate of our sfi program is is
actually the uh
the director in the undp uh program
of the he does the analysis funding and
allocation
of the of the of the um
of the nations that are the recipients
of of the un's fund for the sdg
development and so he's using and he's a
he's a real fan of oz pecan's work and
he knows christakis and he's worked with
these methodologies
and so i'll just say that you know in
the discussions i've i've had with
people like that
we are starting to push for something
like
flourishing goals which might be at 20
30 and that's a long time to wait
but if you can feed forward you can just
you know this is basically breaking the
frame right it's what
you would do with the design brief if
you could
um we often can't but what you can do
within the projects you're in is to
you know find places where you can break
through the frame
and start to approach a more cr
you know a creative um
uh you know a a creative um
um i don't wanna say redress but it's
it's
essentially through through provocation
at first but then through democratic
dialogue
with the other mem you know with the
members of the
uh you know of the of the global action
network or the problem you know the
problem framing group you're working
with
but for if you're as a designer also
working with
stakeholder groups directly you also
need to work with kind of the core
problem you know the core
team that is framing the you know the
relationship to that you know to the
sdgs or to the context
so that some rethinking can can be
rethinking of the problem space can be
done
you know effectively by by by the
different stakeholders and i think it
it helps to do very rigorous selection
of um of stakeholders for the requisite
variety
necessary for that for that frame which
means
inviting people sometimes they think of
it as getting the whole system in the
room
and that usually means like large group
engagements
but you can do um
you know other approaches that i've been
developing of evolutionary stakeholder
discovery
which which look for the
the intersecting relationships between
people who have expertise and lived
experience in
the problem areas who have um
who have an ontological commitment in
in one area or another that that they're
able to bring so you have
you know and you don't just have an
equal ecological economist but you have
small business people and you might have
urban and
rural and and older and younger
and people who are subject to bad
decisions and people who are
owners of those decisions in the same
space of design and going from dialogue
to design so
i think it can be difficult i think we
as a designer might also know we
we um can use a fix we we can too easily
fall into
the fixation of the frame or leading
people down garden paths if we
um use design thinking too early because
design thinking has a way of creating
kind of a false consensus or what john
warfield would
would say is is is actually
facilitated facilitating facilitating
the creation of consensus so that people
can feel productive
as they engage in a problem-solving you
know processes
and so we need to have kind of this
sufficient dissension
in deep listening before you can
actually engage
design so that's one reason i try to
separate some of these system methods
from design methods so that you can do
design approaches in the system
methods and you can use system thinking
in the design approaches as well
that's probably long-winded but a way i
would think about it
so cool um we're gonna have to land the
plane right now um because another event
is starting soon
um but uh peter any closing thoughts for
us before we close up today
uh well thanks for asking i just
said i'm glad i had the chance to
address some of the questions that
allowed me to um maybe say a bit more
about what what i've been doing you know
in the last few years to
um to you know to live with the global
to problematique myself and to take it
forward and to and to consider it as a
a frame not only for the way to
rethink the problem framing and the
problem space that we're working with
but also a way to to rethink
representation
and to and to and to understand
how long uh you know to understand from
histories how long
some of these programs might take and
that when
we may be aware of our own um
hubris as designers or systems thinkers
and planners
in believing that we're going to you
know change the world in
in two to five years um that we're still
dealing with the global problematic in
50 years and if you read those 49
continuous critical problems as my my
students do
i give them the chance when we train in
dialogic design
i give them the chance to reframe
ospicon's original wording
and usually all they do is change some
of the gendered language and sometimes
not even that because it's kind of like
uh the archaic it's a little archaic but
it really makes sense
and there's something unfortunately that
creates a new
fixed frame almost you know they're
afraid to break out of it
but it just shows you know what we're
really still
you know this is going to be with us and
so we have to find creative
approaches to get into the leverage for
making progress and that's what the
design approach
approaches are about and so i'd
recommend you know looking at some of
the work that we're doing in systemic
design
in the relationship of these fields to
each other and finding your own creative
entry points into that and so
welcome you to participate in these
communities that i've mentioned as well
they don't compete with the stoa they
all build on each other and
and i look forward to meeting some of
you in person when they let us
you know when they let us back out into
the playground so
awesome and uh i recommend saving the
the chats if not i can send it to you
afterwards because there's a rich
uh dialogue happening there and uh some
questions and i'll quote one
uh peter jones is amazing omg
uh and a bunch of people were requesting
you to be a sensemaker in residence
which we were talking about so
again i'd love to have you back at the
stoa it was a great session so thank you
for coming
peter thank you thank you and i loved it
talk to you later
right there everyone uh in uh about 15
minutes we have daniel schmuckenberger
uh
7 30 p.m eastern time to start his sense
maker in residence series that's called
the digital porch
all daniel is going to do he's going to
sit down on the digital porch and we're
going to ask some questions and that's
going to be over four weeks this month
so you can check that out on the website
uh
post all the links here the stoa our
patreon site and substack
that being said uh everyone thanks again
for coming to the store tv